hey everyone
welcome to another lesson in this task
automation course today we are going to
talk about another important section in
tosca
which is called the test case design
section now we have already seen some of
other important sections like the test
cases section where you create your test
cases the requirements section where you
can create your own requirements and map
it to the test cases
the third section is the test case
design section where you basically
design
all your different test cases your test
case templates right
and the different combinations of your
test cases so that you can have maximum
coverage across your application
now let's see what are different
components of test case design
what are the best practices on how you
can
design your test cases
or your test sheet right
but before that let's understand what
this section is all about
so test case design helps us to plan and
design our test cases in a way through
which we can maximize the test coverage
across the application and also reduce
the efforts
and redundancy
so that you can do by making your test
cases more reusable
and also you can create different
combinations of test cases without much
efforts right so test case design helps
you do that we'll see how it uh helps us
do that
now test sheets are the highest level
components of the test case design
section right so you have to create a
test sheet where you can uh create
different
components and different combinations of
your test cases
so that you can organize your test data
and the logical test structure for your
test cases right
now test sheets are look pretty similar
to an excel sheet
now if you have worked on any particular
automation tool like selenium or any
other tool
you will probably have used uh an excel
sheet to basically organize your test
data your test cases
or link your test cases to your test
data right so
you will
go out and design this whole excel sheet
and then you will
basically your drive your automation to
that particular excel sheet right
now
the concept is pretty similar here also
but uh
the way to helps you as it just provides
you with all the features within a
section where you can do all of these
things
without even writing a single piece of
code right
now there are two parts to the test case
design section or you can say two
components which are pretty important
which form the backbone of this
particular section
and help you
to reorganize your tests and
your test data right
so these are the first one is called the
attributes
and the second one is called instances
which will look at it later but first
let's understand what is attribute right
so
attribute uh you can consider them as
the different characteristics or
different features of your application
uh based on your the functionality which
you're trying to automate right so think
about um a bank application right
or a credit card application where uh
your different attributes could be the
different kinds of bank accounts the
different types of bank customers
the different types of credit cards
right um the payment methods so all of
these will form the different attributes
or basically your different features or
application which you want to include in
your test cases right
so
you have to uh basically define these
attributes in the test case design sheet
okay now tosca uh gives you some
recommendations on how you can design or
add attributes so that your test
case design sheet is pretty optimal
right
now you can design it as you want but
these are the recommended attributes
which you should have at least for every
test case design sheet okay
um so the first one is called the
administration attribute and this will
not contain any test data the actual
test data but it will contain some
additional information about your test
cases or your test design sheet right so
things like
who designed this particular test case
design sheet
uh who is the business person uh
who can who we can contact in order to
know more about the requirements or the
test cases
then um
which
test cycle this particular test case
design sheet is included with so whether
it's a smoke test cycle or the
regression test cycle
uh things like that right or you can
have additional comments where you can
mention something about this whole test
case design
of which test cases it includes what it
excludes and a lot of other information
so all of these uh will be part of the
administration attribute
the next attribute you should create is
the precondition attribute and this will
as the name suggest will contain all the
prerequisite data which is required to
set up your test cases okay
so it could contain some login
information
or
if you have to create some prerequisite
data from the application which will
drive those test cases
so all of these should be part of your
precondition
attribute the next is the most important
one or you can see the main
attribute which will contain all your
test data for the test cases right so
the test cases which
uh will use the particular data will
contained in the process attribute
then uh comes the last and the final one
which is called the verification
attribute now this
will contain data which will be used for
verification purpose right so once you
have entered all the data um and you
have executed all the test cases
and you come to the verification part
where you want to verify um
the expected results versus actual
and this will contain all that
particular data
okay so as you can see um
different data is organized into
different uh attributes and then every
attribute will have some instances
right and that is how you will
try and design your test cases
okay
uh the other point to remember is um
when you are creating attributes
attributes can have sub attributes and
sub attributes can have again uh more
attributes right so you can create a
tree of different attributes uh
where that could be a parent and a
number of child attributes okay so there
is no limit on how many attributes you
can create or how many child attributes
you can create in your test case design
sheet
okay
now coming to um another important point
about attribute is
uh there is a property which you can set
for each attribute which we have defined
earlier or which we have seen
uh the four attributes right so you can
have a property called business relevant
now it has a three possible values yes
no or result
now what this means is um it defines
whether that attribute
is of any business relevance or not
right or it is a um
result kind of business relevance right
now administration would probably fall
under not business relevant because it
does not contain any actual data it
contains some additional information
which is not required for us to consider
when we are designing our test cases
right
so this will uh the business relevant
could be set to no
precondition in process will probably
fall under business relevance yes
because it contains actual data which
we'll be using to design our test cases
so the business relevant should be set
to yes
and similarly verification
um verification will be used for
verifying the data or for our test cases
so it will fall under business relevant
result okay so it will verify the result
of our test cases so these are the three
different business relevant values which
you can set for any of your attributes
i've given examples here uh based on the
recommended attributes but if you have
other attributes depending on your
application
you can have this business relevant
property so that uh when you are
designing your test cases um
the
not so business relevant
attributes could be ignored
okay
so this is all about attributes now
let's see um with an example how you can
uh create a test test sheet within the
test case design section in tosca and
how you can create these four different
attributes for a sample application
so as you can see now i've opened the
tosca commander and i am in the test
case design section
it is marked with a red folder so every
section will have these kind of colored
folders
which can recognize which
section you are currently present in
right
so the test case design um there is a
folder which is the parent folder which
is called the test case design
now you can directly create a test sheet
inside this as you can see um
in the right click option there is an
option called create test sheet which
looks very similar to an excel sheet
icon right but um it's not recommended
to do it directly under the test case
design uh better create a different
folder uh which you'll be working with
so
i'll be working uh with
this particular application the swag
labs right uh will try to create some
uh test sheet with some attributes for
this particular application so
um let's name this uh with that
particular application
right
so i will call it swag labs okay
now you can have different uh
these kind of folders for different
applications um within your project okay
now under this um
now i'm going to create a test sheet
okay so you have to click on create test
sheet and this will add a test sheet
under this particular folder okay
now i can uh call it anything so i'll
let me call this regression
test sheet
okay so just give it a name so that you
can recognize which test sheet is this
now under this um
let's see what we are going to design
first from the application site right so
you can see there are different user
names and if there is a password to log
in that particular user so there are
different types of users
and then we have got this products
catalog right so
let's think we have to um
calculate
the shipping cost or the total cost
of all the selected products by a
customer right so this is the particular
scenario and we have to design test
cases for these scenarios
okay in this application
so thinking about this particular
application and the scenario uh what are
the different attributes which you can
create here right
so
as you can see there are different
products right
so
one of the attribute could be uh
products right under that you can have
sub attributes like the product name
quantity price right
um and then
that's
the products catalog similarly you can
have all these different kinds of
attributes under process right so you
remember we have to create four
different attributes
in our test case design sheet right
so let's see how we can create different
attributes first okay
so when you right click um you will see
there is a red icon or
a red button
which calls the create attribute right
this is called the create attribute you
can also create different instances we
haven't talked about it okay
there's something called tdm uh which is
uh
basically a database where you can
create your test data right but let's
talk about the attribute
so click on create attribute um and this
should create your first attribute and
as discussed we need to create four
attributes for our
test sheet
the first one is administration the
second one is precondition
the third one
is process
and the last one
as
verification
right
so these are the four attributes for
recommended attributes by tosca which
you should have for every test yes
design sheet now you can have more you
can have less depends on you and your
particular project okay
now before we create uh more sub
attributes inside these attributes uh if
you remember we talked about a property
called business relevant right so we
need to define the business relevance
for all of these four different
attributes and the sub attributes which
are present inside these attributes okay
now
if you click on one of these attributes
and if you go to the right hand side
right where you have got the properties
right so here you will see uh
the last but one property which is
called business relevant
now uh by default it is set to yes okay
uh if you don't change it it will remain
yes but uh if you want to change that
particular value then you can select it
from here right so the business relevant
will change to no
right so that's what we discussed for
administration we don't require business
relevant property
for precondition will remain it yes for
process we'll leave it as yes
for verification we'll put it as result
right so these are the four different uh
attributes with different business
relevance as you can see um as soon as
we change the business relevance the
color changes okay so verification has a
green color
administration has more a light color as
it is no and
the process and precondition have got
more dark red color which is a business
relevance yes
okay
so these are the different business
relevant properties for different
attributes
now coming to uh creating more sub
attributes within this attribute right
so which we talked about
so under administration we can create
sub attributes like this designer right
so who designed this particular test
case
uh we can add some more details like a
business contact
okay um and then we can also add
the test cycle
which could be
a regression or a smoke or something
else
and then we can have some comments
section where you can
put in more details if you require right
so these are the four uh basic
sub attributes which you can have under
administration you can have more even
now coming to precondition um here we'll
say customer
right or we can say users
okay
under users uh
now we can have the type of user okay
so that can be different types of user
it could be a new user it could be a
registered user right or
any business user technical user so lots
of different kinds of users which you
can define
so this is one kind of precondition
which i can think of
the other precondition could be
the address or
the personal details of this particular
users right so we might require this
later on
so we can define it under this
precondition right so this is one
precondition you can have many other
preconditions
now coming to process which will contain
our test data which is the main test
data used for our test case design
so here we will define all the different
products right so let's have a
sub attribute called products
under this we can have more sub
attributes
uh mainly name
and then i can have another one called
price
and a third one
called quantity
right
so these are the three sub attributes
for products
uh and in process
then i need to think about checkout
right
because once the products are selected
uh the user is going to check out the
products right so let's see how it looks
like in the application and then we'll
try to add some attributes here and a
checkout right
so
the user comes here logs in and then he
selects some products which he wants to
check out right so he goes into the cart
he checks the product names description
price
and then he goes into the checkout where
he is going to check out so he has to
fill this information
this we can keep it under the
prerequisite data right so
whatever data we are using for the
customer and then click on continue
and we'll come to the checkout overview
page okay so it will contain the product
details
and some other information like payment
information shipping information the
delivery type
and the total price of the items okay
so
we can create attributes similarly in
our checkout okay
so um let's add the shipping
information
okay
and then we can have
payment information
okay and
we'll have the
item total price
now under these you can have again sub
attributes depending on what kind of um
details are present inside shipping
information different types of payment
information payment types
uh the different item total price
discounts etc right
so you can have many other attributes
how you want to design your test case
completely depends on you and your
scenarios okay
i'm just trying to give you um the best
possible way you can design this okay
now coming to the final attribute uh
here we can have
the
confirmation message which will contain
some details so we can verify that
particular and this particular attribute
okay
so
you can do that once i click on finish
it is going to go to the confirmation
screen where it will say thank you for
your order
it will contain some message or some
details now depending on your
application you can also get some
product details here or shipping details
so that you can verify
and put it under the verification
attribute right
so
as you can see uh we have got different
attributes based on our scenario right
um and similarly you can design
different you can either have different
test sheets for each of your scenarios
or
your business area
or you can have a single test sheet
which contains
um all your test scenarios right
now in the next session we are going to
talk about instances how you can link
your attributes to your instances so
that you can have different combinations
of your test cases with different
combinations of test data
in your test case design sheet right and
we'll take it forward from there